# 這裡有棵野菜哦
Here's a wild veggie.
# 大家好 前兩天都下霜啦 我們這邊
Hi everyone! It was frosty here a couple of days ago.
# 聽老弟說那個象草啊 被霜那個打死了 我們去看一下 (註︰想為「老弟」搞個更好的譯法，Brothers太Formal了，但英文比較少語類稱謂，考慮會不會用"Suyang"算了)
I heard from my brother that the elephant grass, was killed by the, the frost. Let's go and have a look.
# 在那邊
Over there
# 葉子都黃了
The leaves have already turned yellow.
# 你看 這象草 全部都被霜打死了
Look! The elephant grass, is all killed by the frost.
# 這霜一打下來它就乾了
It's dried once it's frosted.
# 好靚哦
It's so pretty.
# 這些都風乾了 (註︰不說明風了，太累贅)
These are all dried.
# 這樣的杆子啊 竹鼠還是可以吃的
These stalks, can still be given to the bamboo rats.
# 這節是壞了一點
The joint here is a bit damaged.
# 這裡 受傷了
Here, it's damaged,
# 被霜凍壞了
by the frost.
# 不管它了 明年 明
Leave it alone. Next year, next,
# 明年的話它又會長出來的
it will start growing again next year.
# 這些全部都枯萎了然後有新的長出來
The new ones will come out as soon as they all wither.
# 一片都是 一片都是黃色的了
They whole area, the whole area has become yellow.
# 你看 這個枇杷花
Look at the loquat flowers!
# 開了好多啊
There are so many of them.
# 你看 還有蜂蜜在上面 (註︰他又說錯了)
Look! There's even a honey bee.
# 明年肯定很多枇杷吃
We'll certainly have a lot of loquats next year.
# 你看那裡 一大片哦
Have a look over there. The whole area,
# 那裡面還有一大片
including the area inside,
# 全部被霜打死了
is killed by the frost.
# 那明年的話它自己會長出來
It will grow again next year.
# 現在我們的竹鼠啊 就吃竹子
Our bamboo rats now have only bamboo.
# 就吃竹子就夠了
And it's already enough for them.
# 不用象草
They don't need the elephant grass.
# 天氣那麼冷 竹鼠也特別喜歡吃那個竹子的
The bamboo rats really love the bamboo in these cold days.
# 不管多老的那個竹子啊 它都能把它啃掉
They can always gnaw no matter how old the bamboo is.
# 我拔點老弟種的蘿蔔
The radish is grown by my brother. Let me take some.
# 老弟挺會種籮蔔 你看
He's rather good at growing radish. Look!
# 好小哇
So small...
# 那麼小的蘿蔔
What a tiny radish!
# 看一下有沒大的
Let's see if there are any larger ones.
# 拔幾個大的來
I'll take some larger ones.
# 拔都拔不到 一個都拔不到
No, no, no! Not even one.
# 大小啦
They're too small.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 那麼小的 你看
It's so small. Look!
# 你看 就那麼小一點
Look! It's just a tiny little bit.
# 好小的蘿蔔哇
What a small radish!
# 肯定沒施肥
I'm sure that he didn't put any fertilizer.
# 太懶啦 老弟
What a lazy guy!
# 哎呀 這裡檢都檢到一個
Aya! Here's one.
# 你看 這裡一個大的
Look! Here's a large one.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 哎呀 你看
Aya! Look!
# 被甚麼東西咬了一口
It was bitten by some who-knows-what-it-is.
# 這個
It's...
# 哎呀 有洞的 壞的這個
Aya! A hole! It's rotten.
# 把這個葉子給它 拿回去餵香豬
I'll take leaves back and er, and give them to the pigs.
# 這個也可以帶回去餵豬
This can also be given to the pigs.
# 嗯 好嫩啊
Um! They're very young.
# 你看 這蘿蔔
Have a look at this radish!
# 剛剛長大的啊
It has just grown up,
# 很嫩啊
and it's really young.
# 這個好小 這個
It's so small, this one.
# 就拔了那麼一點點
So I've picked just a tiny little bit here.
# 不要啦
Enough!
# 帶了一個小袋子
I have a little bag with me,
# 裝起來
to carry them.
# 好啦 回去啦
Alright! Let's go back.